<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honour of the English soldiery, illustrated by way of parallel, betwixt them, and those of other nations, in point of discipline and behaviour; especially of France. Occasioned by severall relations, sent over, touching the barbarous tyranny of the French soldiery, and their forein auxiliaries. Set forth as a warning to England, against admitting the Scots, or any other foreiners under any pretence whatsoever.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E638_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202446</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862721</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114896</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86513)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E638[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honour of the English soldiery, illustrated by way of parallel, betwixt them, and those of other nations, in point of discipline and behaviour; especially of France. Occasioned by severall relations, sent over, touching the barbarous tyranny of the French soldiery, and their forein auxiliaries. Set forth as a warning to England, against admitting the Scots, or any other foreiners under any pretence whatsoever.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soldiers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114896:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HONOUR OF THE Engliſh Soldiery, Illuſtrated by way of Parallel, betwixt Them, and thoſe of other NATIONS, in point of Diſcipline and Behaviour; Eſpecially of FRANCE.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by ſeverall Relations, ſent over, touching the Barbarous Tyranny of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> Soldiery, and their FOREIN AUXILIARIES.</p>
            <p>Set forth as a warning to ENGLAND, againſt admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Scots,</hi> or any other Foreiners under any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barbarus has Segetes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb,</hi> 1651:</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114896:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114896:2"/>
            <head>The Honor of the Engliſh Soldiery, Illuſtrated by way of Parallel, betwixt them, and thoſe of other Nations, in point of Diſcipline and Behaviour; eſpecially of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S</hi> often as I contemplate the good Order and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the old <hi>Roman Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> (whereby that <hi>Queen of Cities</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Lady</hi> of the world) comparing it with ours, it ſeems to me as if the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Manlii,</hi> the <hi>Fabii,</hi> and the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi>'s, were revived again among the gallant Commanders and Captains of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; For, without controverſie, thoſe antient <hi>Heroes</hi> may here finde their <hi>Parallels</hi> in every <hi>Punctilio</hi> of true valor and honor, not any whit inferior in Civil or moral Indowments: But if to the accompliſhments of nature, we add thoſe alſo that are <hi>Spiritual;</hi> by how much <hi>Grace</hi> excels <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> Chriſtian piety morality, ſo farre we may conclude, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114896:3"/>as the preſent perſons and Actions take their riſe from mor Noble Principles and deſignes, ſo they muſt needs tranſcend the higheſt examples of <hi>old Rome,</hi> and appear much more excellent, every way, than all the Monuments and Triumphs of the <hi>Roman</hi> vertue. How great then is the happineſs of this Nation (even in the midſt of miſery) that notwithſtanding, through the continued Plots and malice of her Enemies, ſhe be conſtrained ſtill to keep a <hi>Militia</hi> on foot for her neceſſary defence, yet the matter is carried, through the care and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe which Command, that ſo good Order is obſerved among the Soldiery, as it equals, if not exceeds the ſtricteſt Patern of the <hi>Roman Diſcipline!</hi> Time was (you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) not long ſince, when the poor people were wont to tremble at the very name of approaching Soldiery; Let the <hi>North</hi> conſider how it was haraſſed by the inſulting <hi>Cavalier,</hi> and farre worſe afterwards by the pernicious and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Scot,</hi> who like the <hi>Locuſt,</hi> devoured what the <hi>Palmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm</hi> had left, utterly drained them of their wealth and proviſions, cleared both man and beaſt (driving all away) to the impoveriſhing and ſtarving of many <hi>Thouſands,</hi> in the <hi>Northern Counties;</hi> nor did they abate one tittle of the like inhumanity, all along the Countrey, in that their memorable march (to no purpoſe) to the ſiege of <hi>Hereford.</hi> Let the <hi>Weſt</hi> likewiſe remember, what it ſuffer'd by that wretched crew under <hi>Goring</hi> and <hi>Grenviel;</hi> neither let it be forgotten by the whole Land, how much every part did groan under the cruelty of <hi>Rupert,</hi> and his implacable pack of <hi>Foreiners</hi> and <hi>Plunderers;</hi> whoſe rapacious luſts knew no meaſure, nor their eyes any pity, whereſoever they came. Nor is it poſſible; that the <hi>Mid-land Counties</hi> and <hi>Frontiers</hi> ſhould forget the devaſtations, burnings free-quarters, and plunders, made by the incurſions of both the Parties, as well <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> as <hi>Royal;</hi> For in thoſe days, little better was the conſtitution of many even of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Forces, who were too much infected with the <hi>High-Boys, Dammees</hi> and <hi>Ranters;</hi> ſo that the poor people in all parts, were ground to powder (like Corn in the mill) betwixt two diſagreeing Parties, who both ſeem'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114896:3"/>to agree in the ſame point of inhumanity, to inhance the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſorrows of an afflicted Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But in proceſs of time, it ſeeming good to the wiſdome of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> to alter the <hi>Commander in Chief,</hi> and eſtabliſh a <hi>new model</hi> of the <hi>Militia</hi> (as it now ſtands to this day) eſpeciall care was taken in the firſt place to put ſuch onely in place of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as were men of known principles of integrity and Piety; and the whole maſs of the Soldiery (eſpecially the <hi>Cavalry</hi>) was made up for the moſt part, of men of the ſame temper; ſuch as ingaged upon internal reſpects of Conſcience and duty, not out of <hi>Mercenary,</hi> or any other inferior conſiderations; by which means it came to paſs, that the <hi>Army</hi> was ſoon freed from all the inconveniences and extravagancies of the former eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. The noble and ſerious behaviour of the good, wrought a ſhame in the bad; and as for thoſe whom good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and their own ingenuity could not amend, the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances of Warr</hi> were put in quick execution to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them; ſo that either for fear or ſhame, there followed an univerſal change in the behaviour of the Soldiery <hi>Military Diſcipline</hi> was ſoon revived after the ſtricteſt examples of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Severity; Quarters were diſcharged, Plunder and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion avoided; drunkenneſs, ſwearing, laſiviouſneſs, and all kindes of Luxury, were caſhired; the work of God was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter minded and carried on for the works ſake; Religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes and Conventions frequented, Godlineſs advanced, and the power of godlineſs made the onely riſe of preferment: In the Intervalls of Action they lived like <hi>Saints,</hi> and at the point of Action, behaved themſelves like <hi>Lyons,</hi> being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to triumph, even in death, as an Army of <hi>Martyrs.</hi> In which poſture and reſolution they continue to this very day.</p>
            <p>Whoſe houſes have they at any time cauſleſly burnt, in a vain humor of revenge and oftentation? whoſe wives, or daughters have they raviſhed? What Towns do they ranſack? What Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luges do they ſpoil and abuſe? Whoſe exen, whoſe ſheep, whoſe proviſions have they taken, and not paid for them, or made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution? If any Nation in the world may glory in a <hi>Soldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſure, none more than <hi>England;</hi> yea, none ſo much: For,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114896:4"/>it can be no <hi>Hyperbole</hi> to uſe this expreſſion after a <hi>Noble Perſon;</hi> that <hi>ſince the days of the</hi> Iſraelits, <hi>under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Joſhua, <hi>not any age, Commonweal, or Kingdome, is able to produce one Inſtance (in all points e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall) of ſo noble a Military Diſcipline and Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if no former age, certainly much leſs the preſent; the whole race of mankinde being degenerated from the pure Principles of <hi>Martial</hi> and <hi>Moral honeſty,</hi> and the reins let looſe to all ſorts of luxurie; But above all others, among the Soldiery, as you may ſee in the Nations round about us, where the people are made miſerable examples of their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> In <hi>Poland</hi> the <hi>Villagers</hi> are quite eaten up betwixt their own Countrimen and the <hi>Coſſacks.</hi> How ſad is the condition of poor <hi>Germany,</hi> groaning ſtill under the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riou s Preſſures of the <hi>Swediſh, Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Imperiall</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces! Even as miſerable as the State of <hi>Flanders</hi> and the Frontiers, under the cruel exactions of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> on the one ſide, and the plundring <hi>Lorainer</hi> on the other. And though, out of all theſe Countries, we might furniſh you with ſuch Relations, as would move ſtones to pity; yet in regard we have many freſh <hi>Inſtances</hi> brought to hand, by Letters of a late date from our neighbours of <hi>France,</hi> it is much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to publiſh them, as timely <hi>warning-pieces</hi> to us in <hi>England,</hi> to beware of admitting <hi>Scots</hi> or others into this Land, conſidering the preſent miſerable ſtate of that delicious Kingdom, under the intolerable Tyranny of their own, and thoſe <hi>Forein Auxiliaries,</hi> who pretended they came in there for their aſſiſtance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114896:4"/>
            <head>A true Relation of what hapned about the City of <hi>Rheims</hi> ſince <hi>May</hi> 20. 1651. And the pitifull eſtate of the Countrey.</head>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>
                  <hi>Out of ſeveral Letters written from the ſaid City of</hi> Rheims, May 27. 1651.</head>
               <p>WE are here falne into a diſpair, by the diſorder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Countrey by the Soldiery. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of <hi>Eſtampes</hi> and of <hi>Palluau</hi> the <hi>Forreiner,</hi> have heen here, and have received the <hi>Eſtape,</hi> and yet have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch exceſſes as will make one tremble to think on. The Regiment of <hi>Palluau</hi> have burnt part of the Suburbs of <hi>Eſpernay,</hi> have raviſhed women and maids in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and carried away all the horſes of the poor Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whereſoever they have paſſed, they have plundered the Gentlemens houſes, and have taken from one alone 200 ſheep, with all his horſes and cattell: They have killed or wounded to death ſeveral perſons, and they do hunt the poor Ploughmen, as one ſhould hunt a hare in <hi>Champagne:</hi> nothing dare appear before them: The Cattel of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages of <hi>Chenay</hi> and St. <hi>Thierry,</hi> have been wholly carrried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by them: In a word, it is no worſe a deſolation then if an Army of hungry <hi>Barbarians</hi> had marched through the Province. I ſhould give you too much ſorrow, if I ſhould inlarge more upon the miſeries of this forſaken Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Another of the ſaid 27. of <hi>May.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The miſery is ſuch here, that I think it cannot be holpen by the hands of men, be their minds never ſo much affected to the remedy of it: God muſt touch the hearts of the Grandees, and make them have a feeling knowledge of the publick deſolations, and give them an efficacious will to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy them: I know they hear enough of them, by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent recitals they have of them, but what comes into their ears, doth not come to their hearts, as it would do ſhould they ſee it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114896:5"/>
               <head>The laſt day of <hi>May.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I could add to the Relation I have formerly ſent you of our miſeries, but the little while you are reſolved to ſtay, keeps me from telling you any thing more, but that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to hinder the raviſhings, rapts, burnings, murders, and plundrings which are continued here with as much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, as if they were not forbidden. Three daies ſince a Captain killed with his own hands and in cold blood, within a muſquet ſhot of our Gates, a poor Country man who was coming hither with his wife and a childe of ſix years old he led by the hand, the Countrey man not having ſo much as ſaid a word to him. I do mention that murther, not that it is alone, but becauſe it ſeems more odious. The greateſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is, that there is no Juſtice done, and that the Officers and Soldiers are aſſured of the impunity, of what crime ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may commit. The greateſt hurt done to them, is to reſtore what is <hi>in eſſe,</hi> when they paſs through ſome City where they are not the ſtronger: it is to be feared leſt thoſe who are to prevent thoſe diſorders, and do not uſe the authority they have in hand, do fall into the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, which ordinarily attends the injuſtice of thoſe who want care or courage to repreſs the crimes. Things are grown to ſuch a height, that there is no excuſe now for ſuch as are to ſtop the publick violences. I dare ſay no more, but that I wiſh thoſe who have in their hands the protection of the people, be as willing to help them, as they are knowing their oppreſſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the third of <hi>June.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You ought to expect nothing from me but complaints of our miſeries, for although in my former Letters I have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with the chiefeſt circumſtances, yet the evil is carrried to the extremity, and time producing every moment, ſome new ſubjects of diſgrace. I am forced to tell you that the Soldiers have lately killed the Curat of <hi>Baconne,</hi> and a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey man of the ſame place, who remained alone in the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, whom they wounded with three ſhot of a firelock in the head. They have plundred the Village of <hi>Nauroy,</hi> which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114896:5"/>is in the Dominion of <hi>l'Hoſpital,</hi> where they left nothing, and killed two Inhabitants and wounded all the reſt, one only excepted who is fled. They have forced the houſe called du Nuyſeman belonging to Madame de <hi>St. Piere,</hi> have plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, killed <hi>Nicholas du Pont</hi> her farmor, and carried away all her horſes and cattel. No body dares appeare abroad in the Countrey, where Robberyes, murders, burnings, raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and randſomings are more frequent and more free then in the enemyes Country. Two or three things are the cauſes of that. 1. The impunity that reignes abſolutely every where. 2. The want of paying the Souldiers: 3. the neceſſity which is in the Province, were no bread being to be found the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers take the liberty to run and to plunder whatſoever they meet withall.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of State may be aſſured of two things: firſt that the Province is wholy ruinated without reſtource, and that ſhortly it will be more deſolate then ever <hi>Lorrain</hi> hath been; 2. That before the Kings army be in a body it will be ruinated by the famine and want, nothing abſolutely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be found here for its ſubſtſience either of men or horſes. I think that all the remainder of the people here are going to reſort to <hi>Paris</hi> to begg their bread, which cannot but bring an infections aire there and ſuch diſeaſes as the neceſſity hath produced among them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 5. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I told you in my laſt part of the diſorders commited here by the Souldiery, but as every day begets ſome new violence; ſo you ſhall have no Letter of me, but it will tell you ſome new miſery we are at preſent ſomuch ſurrounded on al parts, and the advenues ſo much poſſeſſed, that it is impoſſible either to come in or to goe out without danger both of life and of the goods; all Soldiers without exception running as ſo many hungry wolfes upon the way, and not ſparing the lives nor the goods of ſuch as fall into their hands: They doe unteame the horſes from the Ploughs and doe carry them away. And Saturday laſt they took within ſight of the Towne the horſes of the Carriers who were bringing Victualls, wood and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarys
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114896:6"/>for the Inhabitants, and left their wagons upon the way: in two or three houres they took away above 100. horſes and miſuſed thoſe who offered to reſiſt. I thinke that if over the deſpaire hath bene excuſable; ſuch as in this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py age ſhall be forced to a defence, will have a lawfull excuſe. The 3 Inſtant one of our villages was aſſaulted in the night by 200. Men of <hi>Pallnau,</hi> who forced it, killed one of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants and wounded all the reſt, one only excepted, they tooke a way all the horſes and Cowes, ſtripped a Gentleman who is a Gens d'arme to the King, having very ſcurvily uſed him before: His complaint having been adreſſed to me here, I have arreſted three Officers untill the Commander hath given ſatisfaction. The ſame day Mr. <hi>de Fremont's</hi> houſe, whom you know was forced and plundered, and the ſouldiers hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing undermined the Dongeon, he and his ſonne in Law Mr. <hi>de Maiſieres</hi> was forced to run away through the Souldiers with their Piſtols cockt in their hands. Yeſternight the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of <hi>Bourgoigne</hi> was plundered and the women ſtriped ſtarke naked. Never France ſaw ſuch extremityes. The laſt yeare though full of miſery was nothing neare comparable to this. I eſteeme that now the only hand of God is able to helpe us, ſince the earthly powers if they can, they will not. I cannot but griefe you by the rehearſall of theſe calamitys, but you muſt be partaker of the miſerys of the Province, though you be abſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 7. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I would end here the recitall of our miſerys, ſhould I not be confident you will ſtay til the <hi>arivall</hi> of my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Chaalons,</hi> who goes to witneſſe the deſolation of the Province, not being able to ſee any longer the violence and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without giving warning to thoſe who have the remedy in their hands. I have told in my laſt how the Gentlemen's houſes have loſt the priviledges and the reſpect, which cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from the inſolency of the Souldiery; they were not long ſince a ſhelter to ſome of our Cittizens, who enjoyed the protection which the birth of the Nobles gave them hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but now they are no more, regarded then others, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114896:6"/>their houſes looke no otherwiſe now then ſo many ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, where the Country people hath gathered the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their wrack, that it might be ſo much the more eaſily carried away. They are not content to plunder the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's houſes; but themſelves are ignominiouſly ſtripped, and their Wives and Daughters are not free from that diſhonour. Many in their preſence have bin ſtripped to their very ſmocks, and we could not keepe our teares, when we ſaw perſons of that condition, who have ſeverall times ventured their lives and eſtate for the ſervice of the King and Kingdome, run away to us in raggs they had borrowed of ſome poore Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen to hide their nakednes. I dare not exagerate the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evill, leſt the readers of theſe fruitleſſe Storys, and thoſe who will not remedy them, as they are bound by their authority, thinke it is rather an amplificated diſcourſe then a true Story. Yet I thinke my ſelfe obliged to tell you againe that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order is infinitly above what I can tell or write. The King's Subjects are no leſſe moleſted, then if they were in the hands of the Barbarians their enemys, for their blood, their goods, their quietneſſe, their honour are no way ſpared. A Mayde ſome two dayes ſince flying (to ſave her honour) from the hands of ſome unhappy Souldiers who purſued her very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, her zeale to the preſervation of her chaſtity cauſed her death; theſe madd fellowes not able to overtake her afore ſhe came into the Village of <hi>Sillery,</hi> where ſhe intended to have ſaved her ſelfe, ſhot at her, ſo that ſhe fell downe dead and her corps was thrown by theſe Villains into a fen. Yeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternight the Mills of <hi>Tinqueux,</hi> of the Abbeſſe and of the Archbiſhop, and the <hi>Folleries,</hi> have beene forced and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and what ſoever was found in carried away, which cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here a great heat, becauſe abundance of Merchants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in the taking of the Marchandiſes, which have been valued, have kept ſuch quarter, that Mr <hi>de Bezancon,</hi> hath beene forced to get on horſeback and repaire to the place where the Regiment doth quarter, to take an order about it. Thus much for the Souldiery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114896:7"/>
               <head>Of the ſame 7. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>de Bezancon</hi> is come back from <hi>Pevy,</hi> where was the regiment of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> who have made terrible diſorders in theſe parts: the ſaid Mr. <hi>de Bezancon</hi> hath beene forced to goe thither in perſon, to make uſe of the King's authority, and cauſe ſuch things as remaine in <hi>eſſe</hi> of their plunderings &amp; robbery to be reſtored. The evill doth dayly increaſe: You heard of the death of the Curate of <hi>Baconne,</hi> as he was treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the randſome of that poore village. Mr. <hi>de Neuville</hi> hath beene plundered at <hi>Nauroy;</hi> Meſſ. <hi>de Fremont</hi> and <hi>de Maiſieres</hi> have had the like fortune; but he that hath had the hardeſt meaſure is Mr. <hi>de Vilette,</hi> dwelling upon the Pariſh of <hi>Pevy,</hi> whoſe houſe was totally plundered Sunday laſt at night, he, his Wife and foure children turned out and ſtripped to their ſhirts: I ſaw him on Monday night, and he ſtruck horror into me by the recitall of the hard uſage he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, the poore raggs of <hi>Canvas</hi> that were given him out of charity to cover his nakedneſſe, drew my teares, ſpecially hearing him grieve for the misfortune of his wife, and of three of his Children, whom he knew not what was become of. The Regiment who hath made that diſorder is that of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> who fired <hi>Pevy</hi> the 5. inſtant, and burnt ſome houſes: I ſhould never have done, if I ſhould undertake to tell you all the horrible and ſad ſtorys, that are acted here. It is eaſy to judge, wee are forſaken by the protection of men, that the ruine of this poore Country is indubitable, and that in our preſſing miſery God alone is to be our hope and conſolation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 10. of <hi>Iune:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Since this Letter is to find you ſtill in <hi>Paris,</hi> I thinke my ſelfe bound in duty to tell you that this night the Village of <hi>Iſle</hi> hath beene plundered by the Regiment of <hi>Chacq,</hi> and foure Inhabitants killed on the Holy Sacrament's day. The Baron <hi>du Tour's</hi> houſe was fired by 260. <hi>Polonois</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Sergens of that Regiment: The houſe hath beene totally plundered, with loſſe of 4000. Livers. The ſame <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonois</hi> have plundered <hi>Chamery, Sermier,</hi> and <hi>Nogent;</hi> the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114896:7"/>plundering continues in the Country without remedy; for what we do in arreſting the Officers, when by chance they come to Town, doth with great paines, produce but little good: An expreſſe order of the King to ſome man of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, is neceſſary to arreſt and puniſh the Commanders, and compell them to redreſſe the diſorders of their Soldiers Mr. <hi>de Bougy,</hi> who commands the army in the abſence of the Duke <hi>de Chaune,</hi> came hither yeſterday, and goes this day to the quarters of the army, which they are removing a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but foure regiments are left, one company whereof in the licenciouſneſſe of the time, is able to ruinate an whole Province.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the ſame day.</head>
               <p>The Caſtle <hi>du Coſſon,</hi> which laſt Summer had kept free a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the endeavours, of a whole Army, was yeſterday the prey of the <hi>Poland</hi> regiment quartered at <hi>Villerſalerand:</hi> they have taken and plundered all; 260. Soldiers did the worke, but the whole regiment of 1200. men was not farr off. The Soldiers want bread, and have no Commiſſarys of the Victuals to provide any, ſo that they doe pillage all the places round about the ſaid Village where they are quartered. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery, Sermiers, Villaneuds, Champflery,</hi> and others have felt the effects of their hoſtility.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 11. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>One of our Regiments having carryed away all the Cattell of the village of <hi>Iſle,</hi> and the Inhabitants going to have them againe, were very ill uſed; 4. having beene killed out right and two deadly wounded. The ſame Regiment, thoſe of <hi>Bougy</hi> &amp; <hi>Navarre</hi> did plunder on the 9. inſtant <hi>Avaux Sur-Aiſne,</hi> where they committed great exceſſes both upon the men and the women and maydes, part of whom were raviſhed, with all Kind of imaginable brutality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 12. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I have much entertianed you with our misfortunes, and I could wiſh the end of them ſhould put an end to my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: but ſince they doe continue and that every day begets a particular diſgrace, I muſt ſpeake as long as my voyce can
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114896:8"/>hold, that I might not incurre into the reproach of having concealed the evill from them, who are to ſtop it. I thinke I have told you how the Regiment of the <hi>Poloneis,</hi> had on the day of the Holy Sacrament, forced the Caſtle <hi>du Coſſon,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken open the Gates with Axes, and plundered the houſe, out of which they carryed for the value of about 4000. Livers. My Lord Biſhop of <hi>Puy,</hi> hath the Proceſſe verball of the ſame in his hand. They have further forced and plundered the <hi>Curate's</hi> houſe at <hi>Chamery,</hi> and carried away his goods whilſt he was ſaying Maſſe. They have alſo pillaged the village of <hi>Sermier,</hi> as you ſhall ſee by the Proceſſe verball I do ſend you. I complained of it to Mr. <hi>de Bezancon,</hi> and as I was preſſing for Iuſtice, the commander of that Regiment came, who ingaged his word to ſee the ſame redreſſed, and offered preſently to take horſe and repaire to the Regiment for that purpoſe, leaving an officer as an oſtage; but as his intention was not right, and that he thought that being gone himſelfe, he would finde one way or another to free his oſtage, he hath endeavored what he could to compaſſe it; but as the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was worth a particular obſervation, I appointed ſome guards upon the ſaid Officer by the advice of Mr. <hi>de Bezan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con;</hi> ſo that the Regiment being out of hope to reſcue their officer without repairing the dammages, Yeſterday about 4. a clock in the evening, the officers of that Regiment ſeiſed on 6. Inhabitants hard by the Towne, whom they have carryed away with them; one is the Son of Mr. <hi>le Treſorier Doulet,</hi> two are the Sons of Mr. <hi>l' Eſpagnol</hi> one of our Sheriffs, two others are the Sons of the late deceaſed <hi>Eleu Cordier,</hi> and the laſt is Mr. <hi>Joſſeteau</hi> Batchelour in Divinity Curate of <hi>Gueux,</hi> who gave out to take the aire. I need not to tell you the conſequence of that attempt; which once ſuffered they may come and pull the Magiſtrats out of their places, when in performance of the King's command they ſhall goe about to repreſſe the publick violences in the Country and Towns; you may judge whether this be not a trampling under foot of the Roiall authority and a forceing by armes the Iuſtice. Mr <hi>de Bezancon</hi> is gone out in perſon to moderate ſuch a high
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114896:8"/>inſolency, for I dare not hope a puniſhment, not for want of zeale in him, but becauſe licenciouſneſſe hath ſettled an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity, and that it ſeemes now it be feared leſt the Juſtices ſhould ruinate the armys, when as the contrary would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, ſhould it be practiſed. Our City is in ſuch rumour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that diſorder, that ſhould not the reſpect and the love due to the King be deeply ingraved in the hearts of our Inhabitants, wee ſhould expect ſome tumult within our Walles, becauſe this violence doth give us no more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to goe out, then if wee were beſieged by the enemy. Laſt friday a Regiment having ſent a party of twelve here to goe and carry away the Cattle of <hi>Iſle,</hi> the Inhabitants come out to hinder them but preſently the whole Regiment fell upon them, killed 4: of them and wounded two more who are a dying, drove away all the Cattle, and tooke all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants priſoners, whom they have ſent back, having kept them and miſuſed them 24. houres: As for the Cows they have kept 11. and reſtored the reſt, for they have a piſtoll a peece. If ſuch diſorders are committed with ſomuch liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty becauſe of the impunity, judg you if upon the high ways &amp; in the Country any thing can be ſure, and whether all things are not fallen into a confuſion, the particulars wherof I doe forbeare; elſe I ſhould write every Poſt an hiſtory and not a private Letter. Pray let My Lord Biſhop <hi>du Puy</hi> ſee this, that he might obtain of the <hi>Queen's</hi> bounty ſome reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to theſe miſchiefes, which are leading us into a diſpair. The wound is great and preſſing which requires a ſpeedy and powerfull awe; the ſaid forces are going from us, and if once they get into the body of the army, hardly Iuſtice is to be looked for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Of the 14. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This word will be the cloſe of all the circumſtances of the impietys and diſorders mentioned in my former Letters; and as it is one of the greateſt inhumanitys that might fall into the apprehenſion of a man, it comes very fitly the laſt, that being added to an infinite number of others you have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to thoſe in authority for a remedy, it might worke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114896:9"/>finally upon their ſpirit for the obtaining of what divine Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice requires of men, and which they ſhould have done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their firſt notice of theſe crying ſines, which earth doth not puniſh. Some Souldiers of the Regiment of <hi>Navarre</hi> came lately into the Village of <hi>Beaumont,</hi> under the conduct of a Sergeant to looke for women or maydens to full their bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. Some of them, mooved by noyſe, ran away and eſcaped by ſome byways. Thoſe villaines who have leſſe humanity, then the Divells themſelves cames, into a houſe in this Village, where they found a poore woman looking to her daughter ſick to death, and neere her end: at firſt they fell upon that poor dying creature, who had no ſtrength to defend her ſelf. The mother being wild to ſee ſuch an abominable ſpectacle, did what ſhe could to hinder them, and becauſe ſhe diſturbed them, they forceably turned her out of the roome, and with words which I dare not foule a Letter with, they forceably did ſhut her out, untill thoſe among them who had inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity enough to raviſh her daughter, had done. Then they leaving her for dead they went away and gave liberty to the mother to come to her daughter againe: but the ſame day they returned to make an end of an action which will make the earth guilty before God, and will make the Land lyable to a publick Plague, if ſuch an horrible crime be not revenged: They offered to raviſh the Mother, but ſhe being ſtronger, they forced her to run away from the roome, and having ſhut her out againe they continued their cruelty upon the daughter, and made her dye in the endeavours of a brutality, which the Divell would not doe, had he a body: This goes beyond human beleife, and truly now adays thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to beare armes, have nothing of man but the face.</p>
               <p>That ſame Regiment have plundred three days ſince the Village of <hi>Avaux</hi> belonging to Mr. <hi>le Preſident de Meſmes,</hi> carried away all the Cows, Horſes, and goods, leaving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>I cannot imagin that <hi>France</hi> can ſubſiſt long in that diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and I am perſwaded that either it draws to her end, or that thoſe, who can ſtop that confuſion, will ſpeedily look
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114896:9"/>to the remedy. Mr. <hi>de Beſancon</hi> with much adoe got away the 6 Inhabitants they had carried away, and hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by the Officers ſome ſatisfaction out of their pay for the dammages done to the Caſtle of <hi>Coſſon.</hi> Yeſterday the Company of the Duke <hi>de Valois</hi> quartered without order in <hi>Cormonſtrevil,</hi> and upon their march carried away all the horſes of the Villages where they came; I dare ſay no more, I have ſo many complaints in my hands, that one makes me forget another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>One of <hi>June</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>Since my Letters in this miſerable time cannot be but a ſad Hiſtory of our misfortunes, give me leave to tell you two things, which take away from me all hopes of redreſs. The firſt, That although our diſaſters be well enough known, and that thoſe who are to remedy them, have their eyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, yet no order is taken for it, by want of will; for it goes againſt the common ſence of all men, to ſay that a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign King, who can do whatſoever he pleaſeth, wants power to do what he ought to will. Therefore no marvel if in ſtead of diminiſhing, the ſaid diſorders are increaſing daily, even to producing ſuch implieties, as hell it ſelf is not capable of. The ſecond is, That having given us ſome hope of breathing, by the orders ſent for the removing of ſuch Forces as were upon us, new ones are preſently ſent to take their place; which makes us believe that our ruine is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable, and that in vain we have complained, ſince the end of our miſeries, is the beginning of greater ones. I might ſay much thereupon, but I chuſe rather to make it ſhort, telling you onely what hapned yeſterday hereabouts by the violence of the Regiment of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> who aſſaulted a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of 10 Carts full of Corn coming from <hi>Chaalon</hi> hither for the relief of our extream neceſſity, wounded two of the Cartmen to death, and all the reſt leſs dangerouſly, took 7 horſes, 22 ſacks of corn, and a cart full of Oats. I know not the tenth part of the diſorders that happen hereabouts; Judge by the pattern what may be the pieces.</p>
               <p>I durſt not rehears any particulars of the Sacriledges and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114896:10"/>horrible profanations of the holy things, and of the holy of the holys, which we know, for fear the continual recital of theſe abominations, and the expoſing of theſe horrors to the publick view, do force at laſt heaven to cauſe the earth to gape, or ſend down his thunderbotls and his fire to conſume whatſoever might keep the memory of the high impunity of thoſe crimes and execrable impieties. Every one knows the plundering and pillaging of all our Churches laſt year, both by the enemies Forces, and by our own, to the full knowledge of the Officers and Commanders, and of ſuch as were appointed to do Juſtice, yet no puniſhment made, nor even an intent to do it, ſo that nothing was left in the Churches for their Miniſtry, nor even the little mettal uſed in the Baptiſtery. The rigours and violences committed by the Soldiers upon the Curats and Church-Officers, by the plundring of whatſoever was neceſſary for their ſubſiſtence, and the exceſſes practiſed upon their perſons, which forced the poor Shepheards to forſake their Flocks and leave them without any help and aſſiſtance upon their death bed, which is not denied even to the greateſt Criminals condemned to death, are alſo very well known.</p>
               <p>The Kings Declaration of the 27 of <hi>January</hi> laſt, verified in Parliament the 24 of <hi>April</hi> bears the truth of the report of theſe Sacrileges and execrable attempts upon the ſacred perſon of the Son of God, and the puniſhment ordered: but that Declaration hath been without execution; with ſhame we can ſay that this year our Churches have not been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe plundred, but by loſing and carrying away ſuch orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as had been begged and given by way of alms in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> during the laſt winter, for the reſtabliſhing of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Religion in moſt of our ſaid Churches, which was wholly ceaſed, had it not been for that ſuyply, and which will ceaſe hereafter, notwithſtanding our ancient poſſeſſion which we do juſtifie ſince the eſtabliſhment of this State.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114896:10"/>
            <head>An extract of ſome Informations of the violences and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders committed by General <hi>Roze</hi>'s Forces in the Land of <hi>Tieraſche</hi> in the Dioces of <hi>Laon,</hi> where they were quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the laſt winter, and have wholly ruinated and made deſolate the ſaid Countrey.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the 30. &amp; laſt day of <hi>April</hi> 1651. and the days following.</head>
            <p>THe Village <hi>du Hoquet</hi> hath been wholly ruinated by the pillaging of the ſaid <hi>Roze's</hi> Forces, who murthered 16. Inhabitants there, wounded 10. took and carried away all the Ornaments of the Church, the reſt of the Inhabitants for the moſt part having been ſtarved.</p>
            <p>The Village of <hi>Morguy</hi> is alſo ruinated by the ſaid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Ploughmen dead or fled, after they had loſt their goods by the plundring of <hi>Caſtle</hi> St. <hi>Clement,</hi> and in the woods of <hi>Val</hi> St. <hi>Piere,</hi> where they are gone for refuge.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Plomion</hi> the Church hath been broken in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all the glaſſes broken, and the Ornaments taken away, part of the covert ruinated; Mr. <hi>du Beltoy</hi> Governor of <hi>Bergue's</hi> houſe plundred, notwithſtanding the reſiſtance made by the guards there, wherein were all the remainders of the goods and houſhold-ſtuff of the Inhabitants remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the ſaid <hi>Plomion:</hi> Mr. <hi>Flander</hi> the Curat hath been ſtripped, abuſed and beaten with ſhedding of bloud, and in danger of his life.</p>
            <p>At St. <hi>Geneviefue</hi> and <hi>d'Olignon</hi> all the buildings have been ruinated and demoliſhed, and the Church brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a very bad poſture, having been plundred by the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who have broken, burnt, or carried away whatſoever was in it.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Chery lez Buchy,</hi> they made uſe of the Church for a Corps of guards for a long while.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rozoy, Romeroy, Aſpermont, Ralimon, Malincau, Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turquê</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> have been wholly ruinated, the houſes demoliſhed, and the timber either burnt or carried away for the moſt part, the ſaid <hi>Moligneau</hi> and St. <hi>George</hi> burnt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114896:11"/>down to the ground, the inhabitants dead, or brought to an extream neceſſity.</p>
            <p>The Chappell of Eaſe to the ſaid Pariſh made uſe of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring two moneths as a ſtore-houſe for the General <hi>Roſe,</hi> ſo that Mr. <hi>Stephen Laureau</hi> Prieſt and Canon of <hi>Rozoy,</hi> could not obtain leave of the ſaid Generall to ſay Maſſe therein; no not upon the Eaſter day, nor to celebrate there the divine Service in any wiſe, during his abode there; though the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of thoſe places were hindered by the Soldiers to goe to the Church of the ſaid <hi>Rozoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Noircourt</hi> moſt part of the inhabitants have been kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and there remain but 3 or 4. of 60. Above 300 men wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children have been ſtarved, the Church and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments thereof wholly plundered by the ſaid Forces, who have killed <hi>Clement Bugny</hi> in the Church, have raviſhed the women and the maids, and have ſtript off their very ſmocks. Madam <hi>de Hautels</hi> her houſe hath been wholly plundered, and the cattell taken and carried away.</p>
            <p>All the inhabitants of <hi>Berliſe</hi> except two or three, have periſhed by famine or miſery; the Church hath been plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the holy Sacrament trampled under foot, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men raviſhed and ſtripped ſtark naked with all imaginable cruelty.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Grand Bieux</hi> the Church hath been wholly plundered, the holy Sacrament trampled under foot, and no ornaments left, the village partly burnt down, and the inhabitants rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and brought to an extream miſery.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Reſigny, Planche, Tyran,</hi> and <hi>Petit Havy,</hi> moſt part of the houſes have been ruinated and burnt, the Church plundered, the holy Sacrament trampled under foot, all the ornaments taken and carried away, and the inhabitants fled, or forced to beg.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Fondevall, Hovy, Lonnaire, Ropre</hi> and <hi>Archon,</hi> of fifty turning Plowes there is not one left, the houſes demoliſhed everywhere, &amp; the inhabitants brought to an extream miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: after they have been beaten, ſtripped, abuſed &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſeverall wayes; A maid of about twelve or thirteen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114896:11"/>years hath been raviſhed in the preſence of Mr <hi>Francis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melet</hi> Curate of the ſaid <hi>Fondevall,</hi> and ſeverall others. It is impoſſible to write all the cruelties and tyrannies they have practiſed in this Countrey. The Church of <hi>Archon</hi> hath been plundered and ruinated, the ornaments taken, &amp; the perſons fled therein put to ranſome. The Soldiers have ſeiſed on three women, whom they have kept a day and one night, and have violated two of them as it is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Dolie</hi> moſt of the buildings have been burnt, the Church plundred, and whatſoever belonging to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, for their laſt ſubſiſtence taken from them, part of the ſaid Inhabitants impriſoned and put to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Yvier</hi> the Village hath been plundred and pillaged; the women killed, the Church plundred and profaned, and all the Ornaments and things neceſſary for the divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice carried away.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Ivier</hi> the Church wholly plundred and moſt part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, all the Inhabitants brought to extream miſery, the houſes, mills and buildings partly burnt. They have cut the ears of two particular men, <hi>Maſſin Minu</hi> and <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Gerard,</hi> and then to have a ranſome of the ſaid <hi>Gerard,</hi> they warmed his feet, burnt his ſhoes and ſtocking upon his legs; hanged ſome by the Chin, and practiſed ſeveral other cruelties. The houſes of two Gentlewomen of that place having been wholly plundred, their Mills burnt, and they brought to beg.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Landouzy laville</hi> the Inhabitants have been plundred &amp; wholly ruinated, after they had contributed ſix weeks ſome money to the Forces quartered in the <hi>Abby</hi> of <hi>Foigny,</hi> where the corn of the ſaid Inhabitants was hidden, which was taken and whatſoever was therein, even to the very diſhes and trenchers wherewith the Friers had feaſted that ſame day the General <hi>Roze.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Janſes</hi> the Church plundred, the holy Sacrament trampled under foot; having gotten it by force out of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114896:12"/>Curats hands, who defended it with the hazard of his life; all the Ornaments taken away, Mr. <hi>James Noel</hi> Curat of that place ſtripped to his Shirt, and ſo carried from houſe to houſe, to ſhew the places where his Pariſhoners did hide the goods, with threatning to Piſtol him every foot, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his ſickneſs of a continual Feaver he had ever ſince a ſeaven night before, and would have died of cold, had not a Cavalier given him at laſt an old ſack to put on his ſhoulders, and an old draibe to cover his nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>The Women and the Maidens have been violated in the preſence of the Curate, and of his mother, who was above 80 years old, and was ſtripped, beaten and abuſed before the great Altar: ſo that it is impoſſible to tell all the inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manities and cruelties of thoſe Barbarians.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Nancelle</hi> the Church plundered, and all the ornaments, the Chalice and the veſſell of the holy Oyle taken and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, with all the houſhold-ſtuffe of the inhabitants, of whom 16 named in the informations, have been killed, others have been ſtarved, and others are brought into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream miſery. The Curate Mr. <hi>Anthony de Migneau</hi> ſtripped and abuſed: one <hi>Neſelet</hi> killed in cold blood, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed to give 50. Rixdalers for his ranſome, not being able to give 100. which was demanded by the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for his ranſome, he begging ſeverall times his life upon his knees.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Harrigny</hi> the Church wholly plundered and broken with the Cannon in three places, the holy Hoſt taken in the Ciboire carried away, the Chalices and Ornaments burnt, part of the houſes burnt likewiſe, eight inhabitants killed, two deadly wounded, the others impriſoned and put to ranſome of two thouſand five hundred Livers; and one <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travé</hi> having been ſtripped and laid down upon the ground, being demanded whether he were well ſo, was preſently killed in cold blood with two Piſtols ſhot by the Soldiers; who likewiſe did cut off the eares of a poor woman, widow of <hi>Nicholas Bohoin,</hi> and then cut her head in two pieces with a broad ſword. Not halfe the houſes in <hi>Harrigny</hi> are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114896:12"/>up. <hi>Chironſar's</hi> houſe of the ſame pariſh, where was Mr. <hi>de Magincourt,</hi> was plundered, he and his wife ſtripped ſtark naked, the woman having thrown herſelfe out at a window to ſave herſelfe with great hazard of her life, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>de Magincourt</hi> tied to a horſes tail, &amp; ſo drawn to <hi>Plomion:</hi> the Women and the Maidens that were fled there, raviſhed, three men killed, and five or ſix wounded.</p>
            <p>What inhabitants are left in this poore and deſolate Countrey, would have been ſtarved and periſhed of miſery, without the aſſiſtance of the extraordinary almes of <hi>Paris,</hi> which have been increaſed ſix Weekes ſince by 1600 Livers every moneth, becauſe of the newes comming daily of the extream miſery of thoſe wretches.</p>
            <p>Now behold here (as in a <hi>Map</hi>) the miſeries of poor <hi>France</hi> under an irregular and inſulting <hi>Soldiery,</hi> from whoſe hands they could not have had more hard meaſure, if things had been wrapt up in a ſudden confuſion under the Conduct of ſome Forein Invader. Had <hi>Attila</hi> and <hi>Totila,</hi> with the old <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> been revived again to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run <hi>France</hi> (as they formerly did <hi>Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Spain</hi>) with a new Inundation, greater breaches could not have bin made upon the Peoples Propriety, nor more barbarous and bloudy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts againſt their lives and ſafety. But that which adds to the misfortunes of that Nation more then all, is, that thoſe whoſe power and pitty are concerned in a redreſs, have ſo little regard of any remedy; but riding in pompous equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page over the heads of the people, promiſe themſelves that they ſhall ſee no ſorrow, but ſeem to ſport, and laugh at the many cries and groans that fly to heaven for vengeance; And therefore, without queſtion, it will ſuddenly come, when the ſins of the <hi>Amorites</hi> are at the full; The time of the deliverance is at hand, and God will cut it ſhort in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; For, the decree of <hi>Liberty</hi> is gone forth from the <hi>holy one,</hi> to ſpeak Peace and Freedome to all the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of the earth, even to the Nations that are oppreſſed round about us: So that if any credit may be given to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114896:13"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted of the earth, even to the Nations that are oppreſſed round about us: So that if any credit may be given to the <hi>Saws</hi> of <hi>old Seers</hi> which come by Tradition, we may well ſay, after them,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> England <hi>is begun a dance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall paſs through</hi> Italy, Spain, <hi>and</hi> France.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And truely, if we conſider the now condition of <hi>France,</hi> the preſent motions of Superior and inferior Bodies (though but with an <hi>oblique aſpect</hi> upon <hi>Liberty</hi>) in that great <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation of Parliaments,</hi> there is ſome hope that the day of their redemption is drawing nigh; which hope would be much advanced, could we but ſee them begin to lift up their heads with reſolution; but alas, the great obſtacles are their <hi>Inconſtancie,</hi> and <hi>Luxury,</hi> which are the two <hi>prime Qualities</hi> or Ingredients which conſtitute the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of that Nation, whereby the Major part of them are in a manner diſabled from the perſuit of ſo noble a deſigne, which muſt be the work of a more ſober and ſerious Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, behold the many exactions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions under which they labour, to ſerve the luſts of their <hi>Lordly Tyrants;</hi> and from thence let us take meaſure of our own Felicity; For, whereas we pay one penny, they pay ten, yea very often the utmoſt farthing: And to what end is all the <hi>Tribute,</hi> but to uphold the pride and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their <hi>Taskmasters?</hi> whereas in <hi>England</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions required, are ſuch as ariſe onely out of preſent neceſſity, for preventing the return of that <hi>Tyranny</hi> which was driven out of the Nation, with the expence of ſo much Bloud and Treaſure: Now, what man can be ſo ſtupid as not to diſpoſe part of his eſtate to ſo noble an end, rather than permit the re-inthroning of an <hi>Hereditary Tyrant</hi> (a <hi>Tyrant</hi> both by nature and Intereſt) to ſweep all away with your lives and Fortunes? A <hi>Tyrant</hi> that ſuckt in his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Principles with his <hi>Mothers</hi> Milk; that was nurſt up with the Bloud and Butchery of a Kingdome; one that is undoubted heir of all the Curſes of his Family, beſides thoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114896:13"/>ſmaller Curſes that attend him; A <hi>Tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> who, if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, will bring an innumerable Train of <hi>Tyrants</hi> at his heels: There is the <hi>Tyrant-Cavalier,</hi> the <hi>Tyrant Scot,</hi> and what other Tyrannick <hi>Foreiners,</hi> God knows. Theſe are they that will tax ye, and toll ye, and tell ye, what a madneſs it is to mutter at a few <hi>Temporary Taxes,</hi> when too late ye may chance to finde how much it concerns the State to raiſe them, to preſerve you from the helliſh miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that muſt of neceſſity over-flow all, upon the Return of an inraged Enemy.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Regnabit Sauguine multo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad Regnum quisquis venit ab exilio.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>His reign will be moſt cruell and bloody that comes from Baniſhment to a Kingdom. His <hi>declared intereſt is revenge for the death of his Father,</hi> which (might his fury take way) would reach to the whole Nation; and what his fury can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſault, his Scottiſh crew of <hi>Foreiners</hi> will overthrow, whoſe cruelty will ſpare neither Friend nor Foe, their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell being now at the very name and nation of <hi>Engliſh;</hi> And aſſure your ſelves the bottomleſſe pit of their avarice will ſwallow all in groſs, without making any nice diſtinction or difference betwixt <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Independent.</hi> Take heed then; you ſee here what horrid diſaſters have befallen <hi>France</hi> by admitting <hi>Foreiners</hi> into their Countrey; learn by thoſe ſad ſpectacles there, to avoid the like here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves. Remember what the <hi>Scot</hi> did in times paſt, how mercileſſe he was when a friend in <hi>Covenant;</hi> what wil he then not do when he comes in with his unjuſt and hypocriticall pretences, as an <hi>Avenger of the Covenant?</hi> We know wel enough what they hope, what they dream of, and what wil be the <hi>Word</hi> throughout all their marches and Quarters; <hi>Ariſe, kill and ſlay, and take poſſeſſion:</hi> For, this hath been their curſed hope and deſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever ſince they were a nation.</p>
            <p>What remains then, but that for the prevention of theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114896:14"/>Tyrannies in the future, which now threaten us with open face, men ſhould lay aſide all traiterous Animoſities, Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances and Deſignes; and ſince the quarrell is become purely <hi>Nationall,</hi> let us then vindicate the honor and freedom of our Nation with an unanimous conſent; if we cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon other terms, yet let us unite as <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and diſpute afterward among our ſelves; for, this inſtant is the very criticall minute of <hi>Englands</hi> neceſſity, and from hence we muſt date either our Triumphs, or elſe an ignoble and ignominious vaſſalage under a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> uſurpation.</p>
            <p>What, ſhall this gallant warlick Nation be betrayed by her own to the louſie <hi>Scot,</hi> who dares not look her nobly in the Face? Nothing but our own baſe Vacillation and Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can undoe us; For, judge, in reaſon what ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutor'd Rabble can do againſt ſo brave an Army? That firſt beat them home (under <hi>Hamilton</hi>) to their own dores, with a handfull in compariſon of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Numbers; and laſt year with ſuch another handfull beat them (in greater numbers) out of the better half of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that God (who is the <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi>) might have the praiſe of the Victory: An <hi>Army</hi> that, to all worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, hath hitherto had a ſpecial protection from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>God</hi> having ſealed them for his own by many miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Succeſſes, to the wonder and envie of the world.</p>
            <p>Let us rejoyce then, and give God thanks, that he hath given us ſuch an <hi>Army</hi> for our neceſſary Protection, and not unworthily repine at thoſe poor pence that go to relieve them. One month of <hi>Scotch</hi> Free-quarter and Plunder will grinde more than a <hi>Twelve-months</hi> Tax; yet their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is not to ſtay a month, but for ever; and one <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Laird</hi> will ſit as heavie as ten of the old <hi>Daniſh Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danes.</hi> Look to it, and conſider what may follow; what the <hi>Scots</hi> behaviour will be, and how different from this of the <hi>Engliſh Soldiery;</hi> whoſe diſcipline is ſo exact and noble, that the leaſt piece of vice or violence is very rarely to be found among them; and if at any time, then it is moſt ſeverely puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. What Cries
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114896:14"/>of the Country do they occaſion, or whom do they abuſe in a march, without remedy? It was ſaid of King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,</hi> before the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> that by his Severity and diligence he ſo terrified robbers, that a Travailer might paſs ſafe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>England,</hi> with his purſe in his hand; the like may be ſaid of our Noble <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and his incomparable diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that any man may paſs through the Land, without the leaſt prejudice from the <hi>Soldiery;</hi> So that whoſoever takes a ſurvey of the rude and licentious Courſes of the <hi>Dutch, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Militia,</hi> with the reſt of the world, ſhall finde a vaſt diſproportion in the Points of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial honor and Order, betwixt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and thoſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations: And he may boldly conclude, that for ſome thouſands of years, not any Age or Country under heaven, can produce any one example of diſcipline in all points e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to the Patern of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Veget. 3. lib. cap. ult.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Diſciplinam militarem Populi Romani debes inquirere, qui ex parviſſimis Finibus, imperiam ſuum poene Solis regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, &amp; mundi ipſius fine diſtendit.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
